Guide to the Richard Berkowitz Papers MSS.421
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series II. Education, 1974-1980, undated; 0.5 Linear Feet in 6 legal-size folders and 4 oversize folders.; 3 audiocassettes; 32 film reels; 1 Half_Inch_Video_Reel
  - Subseries II.B. New York University, 1977-1980, undated; 0.2 Linear Feet in 6 folders.; 4 film reels; 1 audiocassette
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Movie notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Resumes, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Selling It, Undated; cuid41711
      - Ralph Delia, cuid41740 (Box 18, 16mm film reels 421.0034)
        Duration: 7 minutes, 6 seconds
      - Outtakes / Meeting, cuid41741 (Box 18, 16mm film reels 421.0035)
        Duration: 10 minutes, 12 seconds
      - Outtakes / Phone / Bedroom / Bathroom, cuid41742 (Box 18, 16mm film reels 421.0036)
        Duration: 8 minutes, 36 seconds
      - Outtakes / Motel / 2nd Phone Call, cuid41743 (Box 18, 16mm film reels 421.0037)
        Duration: 7 minutes, 40 seconds
      - Paper materials (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Audiocassette (Box 14, Audiocassette 421.0077)
- Series III. Family Records, 1925, 1944-1994, undated; 1.2 Linear Feet in 3 legal-size folders and 1 flat box.; 4 audiocassettes; 15 film reels; 901.4 kilobytes in 5 computer files.
  This series documents Berkowitz's family, particularly his father, Milton Berkowitz. The series contains a small amount of correspondence between Richard Berkowitz and various family members and between other members of the family; home movies from the 1950s; and photographs of Berkowitz, his parents, his brothers, and their families. Materials related to Milton Berkowitz include his scrapbook created during his tour of duty in the United Kingdom and Germany with the United States Army in World War II; his collection of stag films; and his dues books from the Bricklayers, Masons and Plasterers' International Union of America.
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by type of material.
  - Audio cassettes, Undated (Box 14, Cassette 421.0081, 421.0083-421.0085)
  - Biographical materials, 1925, 1944-1952, 1962-1965, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Home movies, 1958-1959, undated; cuid41712
    - Hula Hoop '58 / Atlantic City '59 / Catskill Farm / Mann's / No. 8, 1958-1959; cuid41755 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0049)
      Duration: 27 minutes, 56 seconds
    - Sea Shore / Stella Grad / No. 8, cuid41756 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0050)
      Duration: 30 minutes, 12 seconds
    - Grandpa-y Shul. No. 4, cuid41757 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0051)
      Duration: 25 minutes, 31 seconds
    - Our House and Party No. 5, cuid41758 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0052)
      Duration: 25 minutes, 51 seconds
  - Photographs, 1964, 1994-2000, undated; cuid41116 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook, 1944-1946, undated (Box 19)
  - Stag films, Undated; cuid41713
    These short pornographic films are untitled. Titles are transcribed from film can labels wherever provided. Viewer discretion is advised.
    - Untitled film, cuid41744 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0038)
      Duration: 11 minutes, 24 seconds
    - Untitled film, cuid41745 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0039)
      Duration: 13 minutes, 32 seconds
    - Untitled film, cuid41746 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0040)
      Duration: 12 minutes, 15 seconds
    - Indifferent Part II, cuid41747 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0041)
      Duration: 10 minutes, 18 seconds
    - Untitled film, cuid41748 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0042)
      Duration: 12 minutes, 39 seconds
    - Untitled film, cuid41749 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0043)
      Duration: 9 minutes, 37 seconds
    - Untitled film, cuid41750 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0044)
      Duration: 13 minutes, 54 seconds
    - Wildnight Part II, cuid41751 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0045)
      Duration: 9 minutes, 45 seconds
    - Untitled film, cuid41752 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0046)
      Duration: 13 minutes, 4 seconds.
    - Untitled film, cuid41753 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0047)
      Duration: 9 minutes, 46 seconds
    - Untitled film, cuid41754 (Box 18, Super 8mm film reel 421.0048)
      Duration: 12 minutes, 40 seconds
- Series IV. Financial Records, 1982-2012, undated; 1994-2004; 0.5 Linear Feet in half of a record carton.
  This series documents Berkowitz's finances, including his income and issues he faced in maintaining his residence. Materials in this series include pay stubs from Berkowitz's work as a driver for the American Red Cross in Greater New York, and for his work for POZ and SPIN magazines; correspondence, legal documents, and receipts detailing issues Berkowitz had with his landlords and apartment management companies; and correspondence regarding grants he received, including one from the PEN American Center which allowed him to purchase AIDS medications.
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by organization or topic.
  - American Red Cross in Greater New York, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Apartment, 1982-2012 (Box 1, Folder 16-25)
  - Miscellaneous expenses, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - PEN American Center, 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - POZ, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - SPIN, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Taxes, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series V. Medical Records, 1979-2002, undated; 0.5 Linear Feet in half of a record carton.
  This series documents Berkowitz's medical history before and after his AIDS diagnosis. Included in this series are Berkowitz's blood and other medical test results, prescription receipts, information on AIDS drugs, and correspondence and reports regarding a Crixivan drug trial in which he participated.
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by type or topic of the material.
  - Bills, 1979-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Crixivan drug trial, 1994-1997 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Discharge instructions and notes, 1994-2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Home healthcare, 1989-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Laboratory orders, 1984-1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Laboratory results, 1981-2001 (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
  - Medication, 1982-2002 (Box 2, Folder 16-21)
  - Stuyvesant Polyclinic/Cabrini Medical Center patient records, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series VI. Sex Positive, 2007-2015; 2008-2009; 1.8 Linear Feet in one record carton and half of a flat box.; 37.89 Megabytes in 718 computer files.
  This series documents Berkowitz's role in the creation, distribution, and reception of Daryl Wein's documentary, Sex Positive, focusing on Berkowitz's life and safe sex advocacy. The series includes correspondence, clippings of reviews of and advertisements for the film, film festival programs, travel documents, and ephemera relating to the documentary. The bulk of the series documents Berkowitz's attendance at multiple film festivals around the United States at which the film was screened. The correspondence contains correspondence between Berkowitz and Joseph Sonnabend, as well as letters from Berkowitz to others, regarding a disagreement Berkowitz and Sonnabend had following the release of the film.
  - Correspondence, 2007-2015; 2008-2009; cuid41117 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Film festivals--General, 2008-2010 (Box 2, Folder 25-28, Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Film festivals--Edmonton International Film Festival, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 29, Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Film festivals--NewFest: The NYC LGBT Film Festival, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Film festivals--Outfest Los Angeles LGBT Film Festival, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 1-3, Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Film festivals--Rochester International Film Festival, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Film festivals--San Francisco International Film Festival, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5, Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Film festivals--Seattle International Film Festival, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 6, Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Film festivals--South by Southwest (SXSW), 2008 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Funding, 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Promotional condom, 2008 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Reviews and publicity, 2008-2010 (Box 3, Folder 9-12, Box 10, Folder 6-8, Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Royalties, 2008-2009 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Speaking engagements and screenings, 2008-2011 (Box 3, Folder 14, Box 10, Folder 9)
- Series VII. Sex Work, 1978-2002, undated; 0.2 Linear Feet in 4 legal-size folders.; 2.2 Megabytes in 28 computer files.
  This series documents Berkowitz's work as an S&M top or dominant. The series contains writings and photographs of clients used on his website, analorgasm.net; lists of clients, including their physical descriptions and preferences; lists of services he provided; correspondence with and photographs of clients; and correspondence regarding and copies of Berkowitz's classified advertisement he placed in The Advocate and the New York Native.
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic or type of material.
  This series is closed until two years after the death of Richard Berkowitz.
- Series VIII. Work Files, 1976-2022, undated; 11.5 Linear Feet in 6 and a half record cartons and 3 flat boxes.; 124 audiocassettes; 24 videocassettes; 2 DVDs; 1 websites; 23.88 Megabytes in 179 computer files.
  This series is arranged into the following subseries: Subseries VIII.A. Audio Recordings, 1982-2005, undated
  Subseries VIII.B. Correspondence, 1984-2015, undated
  Subseries VIII.C. Research Files, 1976-2012, undated
  Subseries VIII.D. Writings, 1982-2009
  Subseries VIII.E. Archived Website, 2016
  Scope and content
  This series documents Berkowitz's work as a writer on issues related to AIDS, safe sex, and gay rights. The series contains Berkowitz's drafts, notes, and published versions of and research materials and correspondence regarding his writings, including his collaborations with Michael Callen "We Know Who We Are" and How to Have Sex in an Epidemic: One Approach, and his autobiography, Stayin' Alive. The series also includes Berkowitz's research files which include notes, correspondence, newspaper and magazine clippings; audio and video recordings of Berkowitz, Callen, Joseph Sonnabend, and others; and Berkowitz's website, Safer Sex Positive. Topics in the research files include HIV/AIDS; safe sex advocacy; gay rights issues; and other topics of interest to Berkowitz.
  - Subseries VIII. A. Audio and Video Recordings, 1982-2005, undated; 0.3 Linear Feet in one third of a record carton.; 102 audiocassettes; 24 videocassettes; 2 DVDs
    This subseries has not been arranged. Audio recordings that could be intellectually arranged within a series or subseries have been removed from this subseries and physically arranged and described with those materials. Audio recordings in this series contain conversations with multiple people and/or off-air recordings of interviews or programs. Any extra documentation attached to the cassettes (apart from the sleeves in the cases) have been removed and housed separately. All video recordings have been kept in this series.
    This subseries contains audio recordings of Berkowitz's conversations with Callen, Sonnabend, Gabriel Rotello, Michelle Cochrane, and others, and recordings of television and radio interviews with Arthur Bell, Callen, Larry Kramer, Vito Russo, and others. This subseries also includes Berkowitz's notes on the content of the audiocassettes. This subseries also contains video recordings of television appearances by Berkowitz, Callen, Sonnabend, and others, as well as off-air recordings of television programs and movies.
    Two audio cassettes in this subseries are restricted until two years after the death of Richard Berkowitz.
    - Audio cassettes, 1982-2005, undated (Box 14, Cassette 421.0079-421.0080, 421.0082, 421.0086-421.0102, Box 15, Cassette 421.0103-421.0115, 421.0117-421.0120, 421.0122-421.0137, 421.0139, 421.0141-421.0172, 421.0174-421.0184)
    - Notes, 1982-1998, undated (Box 9, Folder 23-37)
    - Restricted audio cassettes, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Video recordings, 1976-2009, undated (Box 16, Dvd 421.0210-421.0211, Video 421.0185-421.0208)
  - Subseries VIII. B. Correspondence, 1984-2015, undated; 0.1 Linear Feet in 3 folders.; 17.49 Megabytes in 68 computer files.
    This subseries contains correspondence regarding Berkowitz's writing. The bulk of the subseries includes email correspondence regarding articles by Berkowitz, including a response to How to Have Sex in a Police State, written by an anonymous collective of Canadian artists with HIV.
    The paper correspondence is in Berkowitz's original order.
    - City of New York Commission on Human Rights, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - General, 1993-2015, undated; cuid41118 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Rotello, Gabriel, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Subseries VIII. C. Research Files, 1976-2012, undated; 7.82 Linear Feet in 2 and one third record cartons and 3 oversize flat boxes.; 245.22 Megabytes in 13 computer files.; 22 audiocassettes
    This subseries contains research files on HIV/AIDS, safe sex advocacy, gay rights issues; and other topics of interest to Berkowitz, most of which was used in his writings. The files contain paper and born-digital materials, including newspaper and magazine clippings, books, pamphlets, fliers, audio recordings, correspondence, and notes. Berkowitz's collaborations with Michael Callen, Michelle Cochrane, Celia Farber, and Joseph Sonnabend are documented in audio recordings of their conversations, notes on the conversations, drafts of articles by Cochrane and Farber, and email and internet chats between Berkowitz and Farber.
    This subseries is arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
    - 1984 by Samuel R. Delany, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 1993 March on Washington for Lesbian, Gay, and Bi Equal Rights and Liberation (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Adnum, Mark, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Bathhouses, 1976-1987 (Box 3, Folder 21, Box 10, Folder 10-11, Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Callen, Michael, 1983-2015, undated; cuid41119 (Box 3, Folder 22-27, Box 4, Folder 1-4, Box 11, Folder 1-3, Box 14, Cassette 421.0053-421.0069, Box 13, Folder 4, Box 15, Cassette 421.0173)
    - Clinton, Bill--Impeachment, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 5, Box 11, Folder 4, Box 13)
    - Cochrane, Michelle, 1993-2003; cuid41120 (Box 4, Folder 6-8, Box 14, Cassette 421.0071)
    - Condoms, 1982-1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Contagion, 1982-2001 (Box 4, Folder 10, Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Curriculum vitae, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Cytomegalovirus, 1975-1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Disclosure, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Duberman, Martin, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Early People with AIDS movement, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - Fain, Nathan, 1983-2003 (Box 4, Folder 16, Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Farber, Celia, 1988-2008, undated; cuid41121 (Box 4, Folder 17-18, Box 11, Folder 8-10, Box 14, Cassette 421.0078)
    - Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC), 1982-1998 (Box 4, Folder 19, Box 11, Folder 11)
    - General, 1993-2012, undated (Box 4, Folder 20, Box 11, Folder 12-13, Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Giuliani, Rudolph W., 1995-2000 (Box 4, Folder 21, Box 11, Folder 14, Box 13, Folder 7)
    - HIV/AIDS, 1981-2014 (Box 4, Folder 22-24, Box 12, Folder 1-2, Box 13, Folder 8)
    - The Homosexual Matrix by C. A. Tripp, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Infectious diseases, 1974-1984 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Kushner, Tony, 1992-2010 (Box 5, Folder 3-5, Box 12, Folder 3, Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Lambda Passages, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Legal issues, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - LGBT issues, 1996-2012, undated (Box 5, Folder 8, Box 12, Folder 4, Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Lister, Ardele, 2008; cuid41137
    - Lymphadenopathy, 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Madonna, 1981-2009 (Box 5, Folder 10-11, Box 12, Folder 5-7, Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Obama, Barack, 2008-2010 (Box 5, Folder 12, Box 12, Folder 8, Box 13)
    - People with AIDS, 1989-2004 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Physicians for Human Rights, 1982-1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Pride, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Recreational drugs, 1998-2005, undated (Box 5, Folder 16, Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Rotello, Gabriel, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Russo, Vito, 1975-1990 (Box 5, Folder 18, Box 12, Folder 9, Box 14, Cassette 421.0000)
    - Safe sex, 1982-2013 (Box 5, Folder 19-21, Box 12, Folder 10-11, Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Sex clubs, 1982-1993 (Box 5, Folder 22, Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Sex Panic!, 1996-2008; cuid41122 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Sexually transmitted infections, 1976-2008 (Box 5, Folder 24-25, Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Sonnabend, Joseph, 1991-2008, undated; cuid41123 (Box 5, Folder 26-27, Box 14, Cassette 421.0070-421.0072, Box 15, Cassette 421.0138, 421.0140)
    - Sperm, 1980-1992 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Ultra-violet light and immune suppression, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Unsafe sex, 1997-2005 (Box 5, Folder 30, Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Subseries VIII. D. Writings, 1982-2009; 3.9 Linear Feet in 3 and three quarters record cartons and 1 oversize folder.; 6.25 Megabytes in 98 computer files.
    This subseries is arranged in alphabetical order by title of work or type of material.
    This subseries contains Berkowitz's drafts, notes, and published versions of his writings, including his collaborations with Michael Callen "We Know Who We Are" and How to Have Sex in an Epidemic: One Approach, and his autobiography, Stayin' Alive. It features research material used by Berkowitz in his writing and correspondence regarding his work.
    - "AIDS: One Man's Odyssey", 1984 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - "AIDS: Return of the Sex Police", 1995-1997; cuid41148 (Box 5, Folder 32-34)
    - "Best of Manhattan: Best Gay Bookstore", 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "The Birth of Safe Sex", 1996 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "A Brief History of AIDS Dogma", 1993-1996, undated; cuid41124 (Box 6, Folder 3-7)
    - "The Co-factor Factor", 1995-1997; cuid41125 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Crixivan Study and Arrest in Philadelphia, 1998; cuid41138
    - Florida bathhouse talks, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 9-12, Box 12, Folder 15)
    - "Heterosexual Men and AIDS", 1987-2003, undated; cuid41126 (Box 6, Folder 13-19)
    - "A History of the Creation of the Term "People with AIDS"", 1998 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - How to Have Sex in an Epidemic: One Approach, 1983-2002, undated (Box 6, Folder 21, Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - Ideas, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Letters to the editor, 1982-1998 (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    - Little Sissy, 1995; cuid41127 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - "Mrs. Duesinger", 1993 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "The Night Larry Kramer Dissed Me", 2005; cuid41142
    - Notes, 1995-1998; cuid41139
    - "The Original Safe Sex Slut's Guide to Healthy Living", 1996-1998; cuid41128 (Box 7, Folder 11-12, Box 12, Folder 15)
    - "The Other Epidemic", 2005; cuid41129 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - POZ biography, 2000; cuid41140
    - "PrEP: Prevention & Profits", 2013 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - QW articles, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - "S+M: Sons and Mothers", 2006; cuid41136
    - "Safer-sex Panic", 1995-1998, undated; cuid41130 (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
    - "Safer Sex Positive", 2011 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - "Satire on Gay Articles Declaring Oral Sex a Risk for AIDS", 1995; cuid41141
    - "A Second Look" and "Before the Revolution", 1997 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - "Silence of the Lambdas" by Katie Szymanski, 1998; cuid41131 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Stayin' Alive, 1977-2009, undated; 1992-2003; cuid41132 (Box 7, Folder 21-27, Box 8, Box 9, Folder 1-2, Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Surviving and Thriving with AIDS: Collected Wisdom, Volume Two, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "Timeline of Dr. Joseph Sonnabend's Contributions to AIDS", 1998, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "The Tragic Death of Robert Gould, M.D.", 1988-1999, undated; cuid41133 (Box 9, Folder 5-8)
    - "Truth Be Told", 1994 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "The Truth Sucks", 1993 (Box 9, Folder 10-12, Box 12, Folder 15)
    - "A Warning to Gay Men with AIDS", 1982 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - "The Way We War", 1996 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - "Walter Fuck-up", 2005; cuid41143
    - "We Know Who We Are", 1982-1983 (Box 9, Folder 15-18, Box 12, Folder 15)
    - "When Do HIV-exposed Individuals Seroconvert?", 1997 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - "When the Epidemic Hits Home", 1983 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Subseries VIII. E. Archived Website, August 2016-October 2022; 1 websites
    Berkowitz's website documents his writings on safe sex, AIDS, and gay rights from the 1970s through the 2000s. The website includes published and unpublished writings, including journal entries from 2010 and 2013, which include interviews with Berkowitz and Callen in 1983; scans of his writings published in periodicals; and information about his biography, Stayin' Alive, and the documentary based on his life, Sex Positive.
    Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
    Appraisal
    Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of richardberkowitz.files.wordpress.com, videos.files.wordpress.com, and richardberkowitz.com in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints.
    Robots.txt (a piece of code designed to limit crawler activity within a website) was ignored.